Guide to the Stanford University, Baccalaureate Services, Audiovisual Materials SC1091
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Baccalaureate Services, audiovisual materials
1981-2013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Office for Religious Life
SC1091
1 Linear Feet
Videorecordings of Baccalaureate proceedings.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
Videorecordings of Baccalaureate proceedings.
Biographical / Historical
A bookend to students' Opening Convocation held four years earlier, Baccalaureate at Stanford is a multifaith celebratory gathering for graduating seniors, graduate students, and professional students, as well as their families and friends.
It is a student-led commemoration acknowledging the spiritual contribution to the education of the whole person, organized under the auspices of the Office for Religious Life (ORL). In addition to lively music from culturally diverse backgrounds, the program includes readings from different communities and perspectives which represent the wide range of religious traditions are represented within the ORL by over 30 organizations of Stanford Associated Religions (SAR). Stanford's Baccalaureate Celebration is a multi-faith, student-led service for graduating students, their families and friends.
Immediate Source of Acquisiton
Administrative transfer, 2007-2015.
Religious Services-Baccalaureate; Commencement; Students -- Religious life.; Religious Services-General; Stanford University. Office for Religious Life; Chittister, Joan., Sister; Serapio, Nikki Pareno.; Gu, Tara.; Swing, William L.
- Audiovisual recordings
  - Quinn, John R., "3 Parables", 1981 Jun 13; 1 audiocassette(s)
  - 1982 Jun 12
  - 1983 Jun 11
  - 1989 Jun 17, 1 audiocassette(s)
  - 2007 Jun 16, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 1U)
    Scope and Contents
    Following is the prepared text of the student address by Nikki Pareño Serapio, delivered at the Stanford Baccalaureate Celebration on June 16, 2007.
    The key insight of Commencement is that there's a big world outside of Stanford. For many of us, we will soon come to believe in the largeness of existence through the demands of professional life. If you thought those 15-page papers were difficult, then prepare yourself for the 8 a.m. to 7 p.m. workday. If we really did think the quarter system was too stressful, then parents, please shake your heads and give your sons and daughters a wise hug: Tell them kindly that it's their turn to prepare tuition for their future Stanford-bound children.
    I want to talk for a few minutes about the largeness of existence. Arguably, the best way to do this is to describe for you the cosmopolitan content of a Stanford education. I can list for you the topics that I've learned about in classes, and the list would be a good picture of the world. Chuang Tzu; the brave anti-totalitarians in the Spanish Civil War; the brave philosophy of John Rawls; Pablo Neruda's poetry; why wars make states and states make war; why people continue to starve despite there being enough food in the world to feed everyone—all of the students here can take an inventory of their coursework, in order to report that, yes, Stanford has allowed us to more fully realize the heft and potentialities of human knowledge.
    Before Stanford, I went to Catholic school for 14 years, and for me the most important lesson from that period is this: Good works trump all. It is not enough to observe the largeness of the world, when there are things in it that we must strive to change. It is not enough to know the content of books in order to earn the comfort of salaries, when there are so many great social problems that demand our attention.
    Of course, this is a tried-and-true and righteous reminder, and perhaps the bullhorn is about to run out of battery. Every Stanford Commencement is a variation on a theme called "Do not forget the claims of social justice."
    But I appeal to you via repetition: Do not forget the claims of social justice.
    My spiritual journey at Stanford has been marked by the ongoing genocide in Darfur, Sudan, and by my participation in advocacy to stop this genocide. If you come from a religious background like me, then I am sure the most monumental moral question has jumped into your conscience at one point or another. Here's the question applied to a specific case: What power, what creator, what kind of concerned agent would allow the destruction of an entire people? Would allow more than 500,000 innocent civilians to die in Western Sudan? Would allow countless Darfuri women to be raped and spat upon by a government that continues to enjoy absolute impunity?
    Now, this is not a forum for theological debate, and I don't have the intellectual resources to answer a question about the persistence of evil. I only mention the above so that we, the Class of 2007, might leave Stanford with the certain knowledge that bad news can be the groundspring for hope.
    Faced with the largeness of injustice after injustice, Stanford students have responded passionately and decisively. In order to speak up for the people of Darfur, last year Stanford students organized a vigil across the entire Golden Gate Bridge, where we got over 5,000 people to create a 1.7-mile-long procession of conscience. Last year, Stanford students helped draft a Darfur op-ed that was published for the over 2 million readers of the Sunday New York Times and the International Herald Tribune. And today many of us continue to fight for the men, women and children of Darfur, and we will stay committed to this line of work for however long it's necessary.
    My one hope for us, the Class of 2007, is that we realize our serious responsibility to those who were shirked by the natural lottery. Some of us have grandparents who speak about the seriousness of their generation, about the moral battles that it waged, about a genocide that it finally stopped. Make no mistake: We face the same and similar challenges today. When mass atrocity occurs in Africa, or in Europe, or anywhere, our human dignity is at stake; when injustice manifests itself closer to home, our human dignity is at stake. And for every one of us, an essential question will come home sooner or later: How did we use our Stanford education?
    Let us promise today: We will do some good in this world. And we will strive our utmost to be healers of this world.
  - 2011 Jun 11
    In her Baccalaureate address to the Class of 2011, "The Possibility of God," the Rev. Gail E. Bowman drew inspiration from several places, including a scene from The Matrix and a poem by Gwendolyn Brooks.
    Bowman, Gail E.
  - 2012 Jun 16, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 2U)
    Biographical / Historical
    Tara Gu, a senior from Portland, OR, graduated with a major in Public Policy and a minor in Human Biology. During her time at Stanford, she has anchored herself at the intersection of business, nonprofits, philanthropy, and government and has pondered how these institutions can work together to advance social change. Tara has been privileged to study at Bing Stanford in Washington and the BOSP Cape Town program; explore issues in health, housing, education, and financial regulation; dabble in social entrepreneurship and improv; and serve as a Resident Assistant in the largest undergraduate residence on campus.
    Following is the prepared text of the 2012 Baccalaureate student speech by Tara Gu, senior graduating with a major in public policy and a minor in human biology.
    April 12, 2012, Stanford student Facebook status: "So I'm walking between the library and Hoover Tower when Oprah flies by me on a golf cart with an armada of fans pursuing her on bike as her bodyguard is yelling into his wrist mic. #Stanfordlife."
    In typical #Stanfordlife fashion, I've had the privilege to meet extraordinary individuals on this campus over the past four years. But of all the people I've met, the most important person I've met is me. I've become closer to knowing who I am. By who I am, I mean what I care about; my values, priorities, and beliefs; whether I can even articulate those values; and how well I can live up to those beliefs.
    Our society increasingly obsesses over metrics, or the idea of measuring quantifiable results of our actions. We measure percent gain in shareholding value, increase in student performance on standardized testing, and net revenue per physician. But in trumpeting results, we have sometimes forsaken the process. Business ethics have deteriorated. Some teachers have taught to the test. Patient-physician relationships have strained. In emphasizing metrics, we equate achievement with scoring higher on the measurable things that we have identified, and we further reinforce these specified metrics. This is problematic for two reasons: 1) We define results only as measurable things and neglect the immeasurable; 2) How do we know that we are measuring the right thing?
    For most of us, throughout our lives, our metric of achievement has been grounded in what we do. What we do arguably granted us admission to Stanford, and it has been the focus of attention since we were little. At age 5, it was, "What do you want to be when you grow up?" And at age 22, it is, "What are you going to do next year?" Having an answer to these questions elicits "oohs" and "ahhs," as if having a plan for achievement is half the achievement. We are asked about the result that we want, but we are rarely asked to reflect upon the process. By process, I mean the question of who we want to be. Who do you want to be when you grow up? Who do you want to be next year? These are far more difficult questions to answer, and yet most of us spend less time thinking about them.
    In April of this year, Newark's mayor and our Commencement speaker, Cory Booker, ran into a burning house and carried a neighbor through smoky stairwells and falling flames. Why were we so impressed with Mayor Booker's actions that we tweeted #Stanfordcommencementspeaker #likeaboss? Were we drawn to the result of his Dark Knight heroics, his achievement of saving someone's life? Or did we admire what his actions said about who he is, his ability to live up to his values of public service?
    Graduation marks a result. That coveted 8-by-11-inch piece of paper will grant us another neat line of size 10 font to add to our resumes. But those pretty calligraphy letters do not reveal the process. They do not say anything about the philosophical late night hallway conversations, the chicken tenders from Axe and Palm, or the saddening loss of two members from our community this year.
    Results are measurable but not memorable. What is memorable is not measurable. What is measurable is not memorable.
    Congratulations, oh-twelve.
    The 2012 speaker was Sister Joan Chittister; student speaker was Tara Gu.
    Sister Joan Chittister, an international lecturer and author of more than 45 books, has been given 10 Catholic Press Association awards for her writing. One of her recent books, Uncommon Gratitude: Alleluia for All That Is, wasco-authored with the Archbishop of Canterbury, Rowan Williams. Her current book is Following the Path: The Search for a Life of Passion, Purpose, and Joy. She writes a regular column for the National Catholic Reporter newspaper and for Huffingtonpost.com.
  - 2013 Jun 15, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
    Speaker was Valarie Kaur, founding director of Groundswell, a nonprofit initiative at Auburn Theological Seminary in New York City that mobilizes people of faith in social action. Currently a fellow at Yale Law School, Kaur is the founding director of the Yale Visual Law Project, where she makes documentary films and trains students in the art of visual advocacy.
  - Transcript, 2013 Jun 15; 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
- Additional audiovisual recordings, Accession ARCH-2015-098
  - Baccalaureate - Eboo Patel/Zaid Adhami, 2010 Jun 12; 1_1; 1 videotape(s) (minidv hdv) (Box 1)
  - Baccalaureate, 2012 June 16; 1_2; 1 videotape(s) (minidv hdv) (Box 1)
- Additional audiovisual recordings, Accession ARCH-2018-029
  - Baccalaureate, 1985 Jul 21 (Box 1)
  - Baccalaureate, 1989 Jun 17 (Box 1)